realme.govt.nz 2015-03-21

# Privacy - RealMe

## **RealMe Privacy Statement**

#### General

Protecting your privacy as a person using RealMe is very important to the Department of Internal Affairs ( **DIA** ) and New Zealand Post Limited ( **NZ Post** ) (together, **we** , **our** , **us** ). Our privacy statement in relation to RealMe is set out below.

This privacy statement addresses the following matters. You can skip to each by clicking on its link below:

  * RealMe and its approach to privacy
  * the information we collect for the RealMe login service
  * the information we collect for the RealMe verified account service
  * the consequences of not providing the required information
  * our use of the information we collect
  * security
  * site visit data
  * RealMe’s use of cookies
  * how you can access and correct your personal information.

#### RealMe and its approach to privacy

The RealMe service consists of, in essence, the RealMe login service and the RealMe verified account service. Once you have a RealMe verified identity, you will be able to use your RealMe verified account to retrieve relevant personal information from trusted information providers for the purpose of verifying your identity and, where relevant, address, to other service providers.

To enable this to occur, RealMe interacts with other systems operated by DIA and NZ Post: the igovt identity verification service and the NZ Post address verification service. These are separate systems with separate stores of personal information.

When you choose to use the igovt identity verification service or the NZ Post address verification service, RealMe will send a unique number to the relevant service. The service uses that number to check if your igovt verified identity or NZ Post verified address exists.

The RealMe service then retrieves your igovt verified identity or NZ Post verified address and asks you whether you consent to your information being sent to the participating service provider. If you do agree, the RealMe service will then redirect you to the participating service provider and your identity or address information will have been sent to that participating service provider.

The RealMe verified account does not store your personal information. Instead, when you access your account, the account retrieves the information from verified information providers to display it for as long as you are viewing your account.  

This deliberate privacy-centric design ensures that your personal information is protected to the greatest extent possible. There is no combining of different items of personal information in a central database and linking of information between services is minimised and only occurs with your consent. The RealMe service does not provide its operators with a detailed picture of what you're doing online with particular service providers using the RealMe service.

The different systems and the entities that operate them can be summarised as follows:

This privacy statement covers the components of RealMe that provide login and verification services to service providers integrated with RealMe. Separate privacy statements apply to DIA's treatment of your personal information with the igovt identity verification service and NZ Post’s treatment of your personal information with its address verification service. You will be shown and asked to consent to those privacy statements when applying for an igovt verified identity and verified address. All privacy statements that apply to RealMe and its supporting services can be found in a single location. You can review them at any time.

#### Information we collect for the RealMe login service

**Email address and phone numbers**

You need to provide certain personal details in order to use RealMe.

When you apply for a login and create your username and password, you will be asked to enter your email address to enable the RealMe Help Desk to provide you with support in your use of RealMe, and to enable us to communicate with you about the RealMe service.

If you are already a RealMe user (or were previously an igovt logon service user) and have not provided your mobile phone number, DIA may ask you periodically if you would like to receive support via TXT messages to your mobile phone. If you would like to receive support in this manner, you will need to provide your mobile phone number to DIA when requested.

We remind you of our recommendation in the Terms of use not to use an email address that is shared with other people. If you do use a shared email address, your username, temporary password or other information will be sent to it when you request support for your login, for example when you forget your username or password.

**Additional contact details where RealMe codes are used as part of your login**

Each participating service provider will decide whether their online service needs an extra level of security that will involve you also entering a RealMe code when logging in to use that service. If so, the RealMe login service will indicate whether you should use your mobile phone to receive the RealMe code by TXT or through an app or the RealMe token that has been issued to you to generate the RealMe code. Where you have both, you will generally be able to choose the device that you prefer to use.

Where the participating service provider needs you to be able to receive RealMe codes by TXT on your mobile phone, or through an app on your mobile phone or mobile device, you will be asked to provide your mobile phone number to the RealMe login service when creating a new login or registering your phone with a login you created previously.

Alternatively, where the participating service provider prefers RealMe codes to be generated by a RealMe token, it will ask you for a delivery name and address and ask the RealMe Help Desk to send you a RealMe token. The participating service provider will provide that information to the RealMe Help Desk only for the purpose of enabling the delivery of your RealMe token.

**Site visit data**

When you use the RealMe login service or access your RealMe verified account, a server will automatically record your visit, including transaction information such as the IP address of your machine and the domain name from which you are accessing the Internet. This information is recorded for security reasons.

Additional information in relation to a user's computer and the network through which the user is accessing RealMe may be collected if we consider that the user is attempting to compromise RealMe or any associated service.

**Purpose of collection**

The information referred to above is collected for the following purposes:

  * for you to create and to enable you to manage a login for the purposes of accessing participating service providers’ online services;
  * to enable the RealMe login service to log you in to a participating service provider's website or service; and
  * to enable the RealMe verified account service to provide your verified details to a participating service provider's online service;
  * to enable us to communicate with you about the RealMe service;
  * for statistical purposes in relation to the usage of the RealMe login service and RealMe verified account service.

The information collected by the RealMe login service will be held on DIA's electronic database. DIA may use a third party to provide and manage the infrastructure on which the database resides.

#### Information we collect for the RealMe verified account service

**Mobile phone number**

DIA will also ask you whether you wish to receive a TXT confirmation message on your mobile phone each time you use RealMe to verify your personal information attributes. The RealMe verified account service will retrieve your mobile phone number from the RealMe login service to send these TXT messages.

#### Consequences of not providing the required information

If you do not provide the required information referred to above for the RealMe service, you will not be able to use the RealMe service. You do, however, remain free to transact with and receive services from participating service providers in the offline environment. Your use of the RealMe service is optional.

#### Use of the information we collect

**General**

We use the information collected:

  * to provide the RealMe login service;
  * to provide the RealMe verified account service;
  * to communicate with you about the RealMe service;
  * for statistical purposes;
  * to detect and prevent fraudulent or other unlawful uses of the RealMe service.

**RealMe login service**

Every login generates a unique number on creation (i.e., when you successfully set up a username and password for the first time). Where the login is used to enable you to login to a participating service provider's website, another unique number specific to that service provider is created and provided to it.

In special circumstances, DIA may also provide transaction information to that participating service provider, if required to establish proof of a transaction undertaken with the service provider. Such information may include your email address, the date and time of the login, the IP address of your machine and the domain name from which you are accessing or did access the Internet.

**Provision of information to the igovt identity verification service**

If you have or apply for an igovt verified identity through DIA's igovt identity verification service:

  * the RealMe login service will also provide your email address and mobile phone number to the igovt identity verification service to enable this system to communicate with you; and
  * RealMe Help Desk personnel may also provide your contact details to the igovt identity verification service to enable relevant igovt services personnel to communicate with you.

#### Security 

We have procedures in place to prevent loss, unlawful access, use, modification, disclosure or other misuse of your information, consistent with good practice and as required by relevant law and policy. Particular care has been taken to ensure that only certain people with specific roles and authorised access levels are able to view your information and only for specific RealMe-related purposes.

#### **Site visit data**

**Collection of statistical information**

When you visit this website we may collect statistical information about your visit to help us improve the website. This information is aggregated and non-personally identifying. It includes:

  * your IP address;
  * the search terms you used;
  * the pages you accessed on our website and the links you clicked on;
  * the date and time you visited the site;
  * the referring site or message (if any) through which you clicked through to this website;
  * your operating system (e.g., Windows XP, Mac OS X);
  * the type of web browser you use (e.g. Internet Explorer, Mozilla Firefox); and
  * other incidental matters such as screen resolution and the language setting of your browser.

**Use of statistical information**

The statistical information referred to above will be viewable by website administrators and certain members of our staff via analytical tools like Google Analytics. It may also be shared with other government agencies.

#### Use of Cookies

**Non-Persistent cookies**

Going to the RealMe login service generates session (non-persistent) cookies that you can find on your PC under the following names:

  * PRD_JSESSIONID
  * GLS
  * BROWSER_ID
  * PRD_CLIENT_KEY

When you use RealMe to verify your identity (with DIA's igovt identity verification service) or your address (with NZ Post's Address Verification Service), RealMe will also generate session (non-persistent) cookies that you can find on your PC under these names:

  * REALME_ACCOUNT
  * PRD_JSESSIONID

All these cookies expire when you close your browser and none of them store any personally identifiable information.

**Persistent cookies**

A successful login to a participating service provider that requires an extra level of security using a RealMe code by token will generate a browser-specific persistent cookie on your PC with the name: TokenPreferred.

This cookie does not store any personally identifiable information. The presence of this cookie on your PC indicates a preference to login with a RealMe token where allowed for a participating service provider. You will be presented with a screen that facilitates logging in with your RealMe token.

This cookie expires upon:

  * a successful login with a RealMe code other than through a RealMe token to a participating service provider that requires an extra level of security on the same PC;
  * manual deletion of the cookie; or
  * reaching the cookie default expiry period (10 years from cookie creation date).

#### Accessing and correcting your personal information

**RealMe login service**

If any of the information that you have provided for your login (or which is provided by a participating service provider during migration) changes or becomes incorrect you must update it at the RealMe website ([www.realme.govt.nz](http://www.realme.govt.nz/)) using the option to Manage my Login.

You are also free to go to the RealMe website at any time to:

  * change your username, password, contact details or security questions and answers;
  * combine your logins (where you have more than one RealMe username and password);
  * suspend your login; or
  * delete your login.

**RealMe verified account service**

You are also free to go to the RealMe website at any time and access your RealMe verified account to:

  * change your notification preferences;
  * remove data providers from your account (verified identity, verified address); or
  * delete your RealMe verified account.

**Rights of access and correction**

Under the Privacy Act 1993, you have the right to access and to request correction of any of your personal information provided to us. If you wish to see the personal information we have stored in connection with your use of the RealMe service, or if you wish to request correction of such personal information (and you are unable to do so from the RealMe website), please contact the RealMe Help Desk. The RealMe Help Desk may require proof of your identity before it is able to provide you with this information.

If you have any concerns regarding your privacy please feel free to contact us at any time through:

The Privacy Office   
Department of Internal Affairs  
P O Box 805  
Wellington 6140  
Phone: (04) 495 7200  
Email: [Privacy@dia.govt.nz](mailto:Privacy@dia.govt.nz) ****

If you are not satisfied with our response to your concern, you can contact the Privacy Commissioner:

Office of the Privacy Commissioner  
PO Box 10-094  
Wellington, New Zealand  
Phone: +64-4-474 7590  
Enquiries Line (from Auckland): 302 8680  
Enquiries Line (from outside Auckland): 0800 803 909  
Fax: +64-4-474 7595  
Email: [enquiries@privacy.org.nz](mailto:enquiries@privacy.org.nz)

## **igovt Privacy Statement**

#### Introduction

Protecting your privacy as a person using the igovt identity verification service ( **igovt** ) is very important to the Department of Internal Affairs ( **DIA** , **we** , **our** , **us** ). Our privacy statement in relation to igovt is set out below.

This privacy statement addresses the following matters. You can skip to each by clicking on its link below:

  * how igovt relates to the RealMe service
  * the information we collect for igovt
  * the consequences of not providing the required information
  * our use of the information we collect
  * security
  * igovt's use of cookies
  * how you can access and correct your personal information.

In this privacy statement you will see references to "igovt verified identities". igovt verified identities are applied for and used as part of the RealMe service to give you a way to prove your identity to participating service providers via the RealMe service. Read more about igovt verified identities.

#### igovt and the RealMe service

As explained on the [RealMe website](https://www.realme.govt.nz/), the RealMe service consists of and interacts with a series of separate systems operated by DIA and NZ Post. igovt is one of the services with which the RealMe service interacts. It is the authoritative source of identity that enables people with igovt verified identities to verify their identity online to participating service providers:

This privacy statement covers our treatment of your personal information if you apply for an igovt verified identity so as to be able to verify your identity online through the RealMe service using igovt.

#### Information we collect for igovt

**Information checked and retrieved**

Information collected in applications for the issuance, renewal, cancellation or amendment of igovt verified identities is done so in accordance with the Electronic Identity Verification Act 2012 (the **Act** ). In the Act, an igovt verified identity is referred to as an “electronic identity credential”.

For the purpose of applying for the issue of an igovt verified identity, you may start your application on any computer. You will then need to visit a participating PostShop to have your photo taken. You may also be asked to provide additional documents to support your application. If you consent, these documents will be scanned and provided to us with your application.

As part of the process, you will be informed on your computer screen about the identity and eligibility checks required during the application process. You will need to authorise DIA to undertake checks against some records. You will then be asked to enter certain information depending on the evidence of identity source you are relying on:

  * If you are relying on your passport, you will be asked to enter passport number and full name.
  * If you are relying on New Zealand citizenship, you will be asked to enter your citizenship certificate number and full name.
  * If you are relying on your immigration status, you will be asked to enter your foreign passport number, or Immigration New Zealand visa or permit number, and full name, date of birth, place of birth and gender.
  * If you are relying on your birth registration, you will be asked to enter your full name, date of birth, place of birth, gender, mother's name at birth and your father or other parent's name (if applicable).

igovt will then display relevant details on your computer screen for you to confirm.

As noted in the igovt terms of use, there are four instances in which igovt retrieves or may retrieve personal information relating to you which was obtained or generated by DIA or other agencies on earlier occasions:

  * In processing your application for an igovt verified identity, igovt needs to retrieve personal information relating to you from DIA's passports and/or citizenship databases and/or registers of births, deaths, marriages, civil unions and name changes, and/or the Ministry of Business, Innovation and Employment’s immigration databases, for the purpose of verifying your identity. That personal information may include your full name, details of name changes, date of birth, place of birth, gender, photograph, other immigration details (if relevant), and your existing passport or citizenship unique identifier, immigration client identity number or birth registration number. igovt’s retrieval of this personal information is conducted in the context of information matching programmes authorised by the Act and the Privacy Act 1993. In some cases, we may ask you to consent to us confirming your details against records held by [other agencies](http://www.legislation.govt.nz/regulation/public/2013/0009/13.0/whole.html#DLM5025528). In those cases, those agencies will advise us only whether the details you have provided are consistent or not consistent with the information they hold. They may also advise us about the status of the recorded information they hold (for example, that a licence issued to you has expired).
  * igovt also checks whether you have already applied for an igovt verified identity and, if so, whether an igovt verified identity has already been issued to you.
  * igovt may obtain information, at any time, from DIA’s registers of births, deaths, marriages, civil unions and name changes to ascertain whether changes are required to the personal details in your igovt verified identity or whether you are recorded as having died.
  * Where you have given contact details to the RealMe login service, igovt may retrieve those details for the purpose of communicating with you (whether in relation to the application process or subsequently).

**Your igovt verified identity attributes**

When creating your igovt verified identity, igovt stores your name(s), gender, date of birth and place of birth. When you use igovt to verify your identity with a participating service provider, it is some or all of these attributes that, **with your consent** , are released to that service provider via the RealMe service.

**Photo**

As part of the igovt verified identity application process, our partner New Zealand Post Limited will take a photo of you and store it with your application. We use this photo to assist in the confirmation of your identity by matching it with the photo we retrieve from DIA's passports or citizenship databases, or from the Ministry of Business, Innovation and Employment’s immigration databases, or from the identity document you are asked to provide. The two photos will be compared by up to three DIA igovt services personnel. If an application receives two negative determinations on the photos (because they are not considered to match), your application will be held or declined and you will be notified accordingly.

The photo taken during the application process will be stored by igovt for future one-to-many matching, for the purposes of protecting individuals' identity and detecting fraud. igovt does not store the photo it retrieves from the passports, citizenship or immigration databases, or from the identity document that you are asked to provide, beyond the period required for photo matching. New Zealand Post will capture and store your image only for as long as required for the purpose of supplying this image to the Department of Internal Affairs

#### Consequences of not providing the required information 

If you do not provide the required information referred to above for igovt, you will not be able to use igovt to verify your identity online. You do, however, remain free to transact with and receive services from participating service providers in the offline environment. Your use of igovt is optional.

Please note that it is an offence to make false or misleading statements, or to provide false, forged or falsified means of identification when applying for an igovt verified identity.

#### Use of the information we collect

**General**

We use the information collected:

  * to provide the igovt service;
  * for statistical purposes;
  * where relevant, to verify individuals’ details provided with applications for issuance, renewal, amendment or cancellation of an igovt verified identity; and
  * to detect and prevent fraudulent or other unlawful uses of igovt or related services.

**igovt**

When you use a participating service provider's online service that requires verification of identity, that service provider's online service will ask you to prove your identity and if you wish to do so online will redirect you to the RealMe login service to do so.

When you login with the RealMe login service, the RealMe login service will send a unique number to igovt. igovt uses that number to check if your igovt verified identity exists.

The RealMe service then retrieves your igovt verified identity and asks you whether you consent to your identity information being sent to the participating service provider. If you do agree, the RealMe service will then redirect you to the participating service provider and your identity information will have been sent to that participating service provider.

DIA will not otherwise disclose your personal information to any other organisation (unless required or permitted by law), nor use your information for marketing or any other purpose.

As part of your account information, we hold a record of where you have used your igovt verified identity, and the time and date that your attributes were disclosed to a participating service provider. (Access to this information is strictly controlled by the Act.) We do not hold information about the transaction that you performed with any service provider.

When your igovt verified identity is active, you are able to view your igovt activity record through your RealMe verified account, unless technical or other practical reasons prevent this. Your igovt activity record will also include information about instances where igovt services personnel or other authorised persons have accessed your igovt verified identity record or igovt activity record (except in limited circumstances, such as where providing access to that information may prejudice an investigation, or for technical reasons).

#### Security 

We have procedures in place to prevent loss, unlawful access, use, modification, disclosure or other misuse of your information, consistent with good practice and as required by relevant law and policy. Particular care has been taken to ensure that only certain people with specific roles and authorised access levels are able to view your identity and transaction-related information and only for specific igovt-related purposes.

#### Use of Cookies

Using igovt generates a session (non-persistent) cookie that you can find on your PC. It has the name: JSESSIONID.

This cookie expires when you close your browser and does not store any personally identifiable information.

#### Accessing and correcting your personal information

When your igovt verified identity is active, you are able to manage your igovt verified identity via the RealMe website. Once logged in through the RealMe login service, you are able to:

  * view your igovt verified identity attributes held by igovt;
  * view your transaction history/igovt verified identity activity (except in limited circumstances, such as where providing access to that may prejudice an investigation, or for technical reasons); and
  * cancel your igovt verified identity (or apply to cancel your child’s igovt verified identity, if you are the child’s parent or guardian and your child is under 14 years of age).

**Rights of access and correction**

Under the Electronic Identity Verification Act, you have the right to access and to request correction of your personal information provided to igovt. If you wish to see the personal information we have stored in connection with your use of igovt, or if you wish to request correction of such personal information (and you are unable to do so from the [manage your igovt](https://www.account.realme.govt.nz/account) verified identity page), please contact the RealMe Help Desk. The RealMe Help Desk will refer you to igovt services personnel who may require proof of your identity before being able to provide you with this information.

While we do not expect this to occur, should you discover that one or more of your igovt verified identity attributes is incorrect, please contact the RealMe Help Desk as soon as possible. The RealMe Help Desk may need to refer you to the relevant part of DIA or other agency that was the authoritative source of your identity information.

If you have any concerns regarding your privacy please feel free to contact us at any time through:

The Privacy Office   
Department of Internal Affairs  
P O Box 805  
Wellington 6140  
Phone: (04) 495 7200  
Email: [Privacy@dia.govt.nz](mailto:Privacy@dia.govt.nz)

If you are not satisfied with our response to your concern, you can contact the Privacy Commissioner:

Office of the Privacy Commissioner  
PO Box 10-094  
Wellington, New Zealand  
Phone: +64-4-474 7590  
Enquiries Line (from Auckland): 302 8680  
Enquiries Line (from outside Auckland): 0800 803 909  
Fax: +64-4-474 7595  
Email: [enquiries@privacy.org.nz](mailto:enquiries@privacy.org.nz)

**Disposal of your igovt verified identity records**

When your igovt verified identity expires, or is cancelled following an application by you for its cancellation, we will retain your igovt verified identity records (including your igovt verified identity attributes, photograph and activity record) for a prescribed period. When this period ends, we will delete your igovt identity records. This period is prescribed in [regulations](http://legislation.govt.nz/regulation/public/2013/0009/latest/DLM5025540.html?search=ts_act%40bill%40regulation%40deemedreg_electronic+identity_resel_25_a&p=1). If you choose to reapply for an igovt verified identity within that period, we will reactivate your previous igovt verified identity. This will assist you to continue to verify your identity with participating service providers with which you have previously used your igovt verified identity. If, however, you reapply for an igovt verified identity after the end of the period, DIA may require additional processes to verify your identity.
